<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2014) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2014) -->

<section anchor='op:layoutstats' title='Operation 65: LAYOUTSTATS - Provide Statistics for the Layout'>
  <section toc='exclude' title="ARGUMENT">
    <t>
      &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
    </t>

    <?rfc include='autogen/type_layoutupdate4.xml'?>
    <?rfc include='autogen/type_io_info.xml'?>
    <?rfc include='autogen/layoutstats_args.xml'?>

    <t>
      &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
    </t>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="RESULT">
    <t>
      &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
    </t>

    <?rfc include='autogen/layoutstats_res.xml'?>

    <t>
      &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
    </t>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="DESCRIPTION">
    <t>
      The client can use LAYOUTSTATS to inform the metadata server
      about its interaction with the layout (see Section 12
      of <xref target='RFC5661' />) represented by the
      current filehandle, client ID (derived from the session ID
      in the preceding SEQUENCE operation), byte-range (lsa_offset
      and lsa_length), and lsa_stateid. lsa_read and lsa_write allow
      for non-Layout Type specific statistics to be reported.
      lsa_deviceid allows the client to specify to which storage
      device the statistics apply.  The
      remaining information the client is presenting is specific
      to the Layout Type and presented in the lsa_layoutupdate
      field. Each Layout Type MUST define the contents of
      lsa_layoutupdate in their respective specifications.
    </t>

    <t>
      LAYOUTSTATS can be combined with IO_ADVISE (see
      <xref target='op:io_advise' />) to augment the decision making
      process of how the metadata server handles a file.  I.e.,
      IO_ADVISE lets the server know that a byte range has a certain
      characteristic, but not necessarily the intensity of that
      characteristic.
    </t>

    <t>
      The statistics are cumulative, i.e., multiple LAYOUTSTATS
      updates can be in flight at the same time. The metadata
      server can examine the packet's timestamp to order the
      different calls.  The first
      LAYOUTSTATS sent by the client SHOULD be from the opening
      of the file.  The choice of how often to update the metadata
      server is made by the client.
    </t>

    <t>
      Note that while the metadata server may return an error
      associated with the layout stateid or the open file, it
      MUST NOT return an error in the processing of the statistics.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
