<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011-2012) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011-2012) -->

<section anchor="op:copy_notify" title="Operation 61: COPY_NOTIFY - Notify a source server of a future copy">
  <section toc='exclude' title="ARGUMENT">
    <t>
      &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
    </t>

    <?rfc include='autogen/copy_notify_args.xml'?>

    <t>
      &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
    </t>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="RESULT">
    <t>
      &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
    </t>

    <?rfc include='autogen/copy_notify_res.xml'?>

    <t>
      &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
    </t>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="DESCRIPTION">
    <t>
      This operation is used for an inter-server copy. A client
      sends this operation in a COMPOUND request to the source
      server to authorize a destination server identified by
      cna_destination_server to read the file specified by
      CURRENT_FH on behalf of the given user.
    </t>

    <t>
      The cna_src_stateid MUST refer to either open or locking
      states provided earlier by the server. If it is invalid,
      then the operation MUST fail.
    </t>

    <t>
      The cna_destination_server MUST be specified using the
      netloc4 network location format. The server is not required
      to resolve the cna_destination_server address before completing
      this operation.
    </t>

    <t>
      If this operation succeeds, the source server will allow the
      cna_destination_server to copy the specified file on behalf
      of the given user as long as both of the following
      conditions are met:
    </t>

    <t>
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>
          The destination server begins reading the source file
          before the cnr_lease_time expires. If the cnr_lease_time
          expires while the destination server is still reading
          the source file, the destination server is allowed to
          finish reading the file.
        </t>

        <t>
          The client has not issued a OFFLOAD_CANCEL for
          the same combination of user, filehandle,
          and destination server.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>

    <t>
      The cnr_lease_time is chosen by the source server. A cnr_lease_time
      of 0 (zero) indicates an infinite lease.  To avoid the need for
      synchronized clocks, copy lease times are granted by the server
      as a time delta.  To renew the copy lease time the client should
      resend the same copy notification request to the source server.
    </t>

    <t>
      The cnr_stateid is a copy stateid which uniquely describes the
      state needed on the source server to track the proposed copy.
      As defined in Section 8.2 of <xref target='RFC5661' />, a stateid
      is tied to the current filehandle and if the same stateid is
      presented by two different clients, it may refer to different
      state. As the source does not know which netloc4 network
      location the destinaton might use to establish the copy operation,
      it can use the cnr_stateid to identify that the destination
      is operating on behalf of the client. Thus the source server
      MUST construct copy stateids such that they are unique from
      all other stateids handed out to clients. These copy stateids
      MUST equate to each of the earlier delegation, locking,
      and open states for the client on the given file (see
      <xref target='ss:copy:lock' />).
    </t>

    <t>
      A successful response will also contain a list of netloc4 network
      location formats called cnr_source_server, on which the source is
      willing to accept connections from the destination. These might
      not be reachable from the client and might be located on networks
      to which the client has no connection.
    </t>

    <t>
      For a copy only involving one server (the source and destination
      are on the same server), this operation is unnecessary.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
