<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011-2012) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011-2012) -->

<section anchor="op:copy_notify" title="Operation 61: COPY_NOTIFY - Notify a source server of a future copy">
  <section toc='exclude' title="ARGUMENT">
    <?rfc include='autogen/copy_notify_args.xml'?>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="RESULT">
    <?rfc include='autogen/copy_notify_res.xml'?>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="DESCRIPTION">
    <t>
      This operation is used for an inter-server copy. A client
      sends this operation in a COMPOUND request to the source
      server to authorize a destination server identified by
      cna_destination_server to read the file specified by
      CURRENT_FH on behalf of the given user.
    </t>

    <t>
      The cna_src_stateid MUST refer to either open or locking
      states provided earlier by the server. If it is invalid,
      then the operation MUST fail.
    </t>

    <t>
      The cna_destination_server MUST be specified using the
      netloc4 network location format. The server is not required
      to resolve the cna_destination_server address before completing
      this operation.
    </t>

    <t>
      If this operation succeeds, the source server will allow the
      cna_destination_server to copy the specified file on behalf
      of the given user as long as both of the following
      conditions are met:
    </t>

    <t>
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>
          The destination server begins reading the source file
          before the cnr_lease_time expires. If the cnr_lease_time
          expires while the destination server is still reading
          the source file, the destination server is allowed to
          finish reading the file.
        </t>

        <t>
          The client has not issued a COPY_REVOKE for
          the same combination of user, filehandle,
          and destination server.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>

    <t>
      The cnr_lease_time is chosen by the source server. A
      cnr_lease_time of 0 (zero) indicates an infinite lease.
      To avoid the need for synchronized clocks, copy lease times
      are granted by the server as a time delta.
      To renew the copy lease time the client should resend the same
      copy notification request to the source server.
    </t>

    <t>
      A successful response will also contain a list of netloc4
      network location formats
      called cnr_source_server, on which the source is willing to
      accept connections from the destination. These might not be reachable
      from the client and might be located on networks to which the client
      has no connection.
    </t>

    <t>
      If the client wishes to perform an inter-server copy, the client
      MUST send a COPY_NOTIFY to the source server. Therefore, the source
      server MUST support COPY_NOTIFY.
    </t>

    <t>
      For a copy only involving one server (the source and destination
      are on the same server), this operation is unnecessary.
    </t>

    <t>
      The COPY_NOTIFY operation may fail for the following reasons
      (this is a partial list):
    </t>

    <t>
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>NFS4ERR_MOVED</t>
        <t>NFS4ERR_NOTSUPP</t>
        <t>NFS4ERR_WRONGSEC</t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
