<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011-2014) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011-2014) -->

<section anchor="op:clone"
	 title="Operation 71: CLONE - Clone a range of file into another file">
  <section toc='exclude' title="ARGUMENT">
    <t>
      &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
    </t>

    <?rfc include='autogen/clone_args.xml'?>

    <t>
      &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
    </t>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="RESULT">
    <t>
      &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
    </t>

    <?rfc include='autogen/clone_res.xml'?>

    <t>
      &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
    </t>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="DESCRIPTION">
    <t>
      The CLONE operation is used to clone file content from a source
      file specified by the SAVED_FH value into a destination file
      specified by CURRENT_FH without actually copying the data, e.g.,
      by using a copy-on-write mechanism.
    </t>

    <t>
      Both SAVED_FH and CURRENT_FH must be regular files. If either
      SAVED_FH or CURRENT_FH is not a regular file, the operation
      MUST fail and return NFS4ERR_WRONG_TYPE.
    </t>

    <t>
      SAVED_FH and CURRENT_FH must be different files.  If SAVED_FH and
      CURRENT_FH refer to the same file, the operation MUST fail with
      NFS4ERR_INVAL.
    </t>

    <t>
      The ca_dst_stateid MUST refer to a stateid that is valid for
      a WRITE operation and follows the rules for stateids in
      Sections 8.2.5 and 18.32.3 of <xref target='RFC5661' />.
      The ca_src_stateid MUST refer to a
      stateid that is valid for a READ operations and follows the rules
      for stateids in Sections 8.2.5 and 18.22.3 of
      <xref target='RFC5661' />. If either stateid is invalid, then the
      operation MUST fail.
    </t>

    <t>
      The cl_src_offset is the starting offset within the source file from which
      the data to be cloned will be obtained and the cl_dst_offset is the
      starting offset of the target region into which the cloned data will be
      placed. An offset of 0 (zero) indicates the start of the respective file.
      The number of bytes to be cloned is obtained from cl_count, except that a
      cl_count of 0 (zero) indicates that the number of bytes to be cloned is the
      count of bytes between cl_src_offset and the EOF of the source file. Both
      cl_src_offset and cl_dst_offset must be aligned to the clone block size
      <xref target='ss:fattr:clone' />. The number of bytes to be cloned must be a
      multiple of the clone block size, except in the case in which cl_src_offset
      plus the number of bytes to be cloned is equal to the source file size.
    </t>

    <t>
      If the source offset or the source offset plus count is greater
      than the size of the source file, the operation MUST fail with
      NFS4ERR_INVAL. The destination offset or destination offset plus
      count may be greater than the size of the destination file.
    </t>

    <t>
      If the target area of the clone operation ends beyond the end of the
      destination file, the offset at the end of the target area will determine
      the new size of the destination file.  The contents of any block not part
      of the target area will be the same as if the file size were extended by a
      WRITE.
    </t>

    <t>
      If the area to be cloned is not a multiple of the clone block size and the
      size of the destination file is past the end of the target area, the area
      between the end of the target area and the next multiple of the clone block
      size wlll be zeroed.
    </t>

    <t>
      The CLONE operation is atomic in that other operations may not see see any
      intermediate states between the state of the two files before the operation
      and that after the operation. READs of the destination file will never
      see some blocks of the target area cloned without all of them being
      cloned.  WRITEs of the source area will either have no effect on the data
      of the target file or be fully reflected in the target area of the
      destination file.
    </t>

    <t>
      The completion status of the operation is indicated by cr_status.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
