<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011-2012) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011-2012) -->

<section title="Acknowledgments">
  <t>
    For the pNFS Access Permissions Check, the original draft was
    by Sorin Faibish, David Black, Mike Eisler, and Jason Glasgow.
    The work was influenced by discussions with Benny Halevy and
    Bruce Fields. A review was done by Tom Haynes.
  </t>
  <t>
    For the Sharing change attribute implementation details with NFSv4
    clients, the original draft was by Trond Myklebust.
  </t>
  <t>
    For the NFS Server-side Copy, the original draft was by
    James Lentini, Mike Eisler, Deepak Kenchammana, Anshul Madan,
    and Rahul Iyer. Tom Talpey co-authored an unpublished version
    of that document.  It was also was reviewed by a number of individuals:
    Pranoop Erasani, Tom Haynes, Arthur Lent, Trond Myklebust,
    Dave Noveck, Theresa Lingutla-Raj, Manjunath Shankararao, Satyam
    Vaghani, and Nico Williams.
  </t>
  <t>
    For the NFS space reservation operations, the original draft was
    by Mike Eisler, James Lentini, Manjunath Shankararao, and Rahul Iyer.
  </t>
  <t>
    For the sparse file support, the original draft was by Dean Hildebrand
    and Marc Eshel. Valuable input and advice was received from Sorin
    Faibish, Bruce Fields, Benny Halevy, Trond Myklebust, and Richard
    Scheffenegger.
  </t>
  <t>
    For the Application IO Hints, the original draft was by Dean Hildebrand,
    Mike Eisler, Trond Myklebust, and Sam Falkner. Some early reviewers
    included Benny Halevy and Pranoop Erasani.
  </t>
  <t>
    For Labeled NFS, the original draft was by David Quigley, James Morris,
    Jarret Lu, and Tom Haynes. Peter Staubach, Trond Myklebust, Stephen Smalley,
    Sorrin Faibish, Nico Williams, and David Black also contributed in the
    final push to get this accepted.
  </t>

  <t>
    During the review process, Talia Reyes-Ortiz helped the sessions
    run smoothly. While many people contributed here and there, the
    core reviewers were Andy Adamson, Pranoop Erasani, Bruce Fields, Chuck Lever,
    Trond Myklebust, David Noveck, Peter Staubach, and Mike Kupfer.
  </t>
</section>

<section title="RFC Editor Notes">

<t>
[RFC Editor: please remove this section prior to publishing
this document as an RFC]

</t>

<t>
[RFC Editor: prior to publishing this document as an RFC, please replace all occurrences of RFCTBD10
with RFCxxxx where xxxx is the RFC number of this document]
</t>

</section>
