<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011-2014) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011-2014) -->

<section anchor='op:read_plus' title='Operation 68: READ_PLUS - READ Data or Holes from a File'>
  <section toc='exclude' title="ARGUMENT">
    <t>
      &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
    </t>

    <?rfc include='autogen/read_plus_args.xml'?>

    <t>
      &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
    </t>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="RESULT">
    <t>
      &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
    </t>

    <?rfc include='autogen/data_content4.xml'?>
    <?rfc include='autogen/data_info4.xml'?>
    <?rfc include='autogen/data4.xml'?>
    <?rfc include='autogen/read_plus_content.xml'?>
    <?rfc include='autogen/read_plus_res_pre.xml'?>
    <?rfc include='autogen/read_plus_res.xml'?>

    <t>
      &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
    </t>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' anchor='op:read_plus:desc'  title="DESCRIPTION">
    <t>
      The READ_PLUS operation is based upon the NFSv4.1 READ operation
      (see Section 18.22 of <xref target="RFC5661" />) and similarly
      reads data from the regular file identified by the current
      filehandle.
    </t>

    <t>
      The client provides a rpa_offset of where the READ_PLUS is
      to start and a rpa_count of how many bytes are to be read.
      A rpa_offset of zero means to read data starting at the
      beginning of the file.  If rpa_offset is greater than or equal
      to the size of the file, the status NFS4_OK is returned with
      di_length (the data length) set to zero and eof set to TRUE.
    </t>

    <t>
      The READ_PLUS result is comprised of an array of rpr_contents,
      each of which describe a data_content4 type of data.  For
      NFSv4.2, the allowed values are data and hole. A server MUST
      support both the data type and the hole if it uses READ_PLUS.
      If it does not want to support a hole, it MUST use READ.  The
      array contents MUST be contiguous in the file.
    </t>

    <t>
      Holes SHOULD be returned in their entirety - clients must be
      prepared to get more information than they requested. Both
      the start and the end of the hole may exceed what was requested.
      If data to be returned is comprised entirely of zeros, then the
      server SHOULD return that data as a hole instead.
    </t>

    <t>
      The server may elect to return adjacent elements of the same
      type. For example, if the server has a range of data comprised
      entirely of zeros and then a hole, it might want to return
      two adjacent holes to the client.
    </t>

    <t>
      If the client specifies a rpa_count value of zero, the READ_PLUS succeeds
      and returns zero bytes of data.  In all situations, the server may choose
      to return fewer
      bytes than specified by the client.  The client needs to check for
      this condition and handle the condition appropriately.
    </t>

    <t>
      If the client specifies an rpa_offset and rpa_count value
      that is entirely contained within a hole of the file, then
      the di_offset and di_length returned MAY be for the entire
      hole.  If the the owner has a locked byte range covering
      rpa_offset and rpa_count entirely the di_offset and di_length
      MUST NOT be extended outside the locked byte range.  This
      result is considered valid until the file is changed (detected
      via the change attribute).  The server MUST provide the same
      semantics for the hole as if the client read the region and
      received zeroes; the implied holes contents lifetime MUST be
      exactly the same as any other read data.
    </t>

    <t>
      If the client specifies an rpa_offset and rpa_count value that
      begins in a non-hole of the file but extends into hole the server
      should return an array comprised of both data and a hole. The
      client MUST be prepared for the server to return a short read
      describing just the data.  The client will
      then issue another READ_PLUS for the remaining bytes, which the server
      will respond with information about the hole in the file.
    </t>

    <t>
      Except when special stateids are used, the stateid value for a
      READ_PLUS request represents a value returned from a previous
      byte-range lock or share reservation request or the stateid associated
      with a delegation.  The stateid identifies the associated owners if
      any and is used by the server to verify that the associated locks are
      still valid (e.g., have not been revoked).
    </t>

    <t>
      If the read ended at the end-of-file (formally, in a correctly formed
      READ_PLUS operation, if rpa_offset + rpa_count is equal to the size of the
      file), or the READ_PLUS operation extends beyond the size of the file
      (if rpa_offset + rpa_count is greater than the size of the file), eof is
      returned as TRUE; otherwise, it is FALSE.  A successful READ_PLUS of
      an empty file will always return eof as TRUE.
    </t>

    <t>
      If the current filehandle is not an ordinary file, an error will be
      returned to the client.  In the case that the current filehandle
      represents an object of type NF4DIR, NFS4ERR_ISDIR is returned.  If
      the current filehandle designates a symbolic link, NFS4ERR_SYMLINK is
      returned.  In all other cases, NFS4ERR_WRONG_TYPE is returned.
    </t>

    <t>
      For a READ_PLUS with a stateid value of all bits equal to zero, the
      server MAY allow the READ_PLUS to be serviced subject to mandatory
      byte-range locks or the current share deny modes for the file.  For a
      READ_PLUS with a stateid value of all bits equal to one, the server
      MAY allow READ_PLUS operations to bypass locking checks at the server.
    </t>

    <t>
      On success, the current filehandle retains its value.
    </t>

    <section toc='exclude' title="Note on Client Support of Arms of the Union">
      <t>
        It was decided not to add a means for the client to inform
        the server as to which arms of READ_PLUS it would support.
        In a later minor version, it may become necessary for the
        introduction of a new operation which would allow the client
        to inform the server as to whether it supported the new
        arms of the union of data types available in READ_PLUS.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="IMPLEMENTATION">
    <t>
      In general, the IMPLEMENTATION notes for READ in Section 18.22.4 of
      <xref target="RFC5661" /> also apply to READ_PLUS.
    </t>

    <section toc='exclude' title="Additional pNFS Implementation Information">
      <t>
        With pNFS, the semantics of using READ_PLUS remains the same.  Any
        data server MAY return a hole result for a READ_PLUS request that
        it receives.  When a data server chooses to return such a result, it has the
        option of returning information for the data stored on that
        data server (as defined by the data layout), but it MUST NOT return
        results for a byte range that includes data managed by another data server.
      </t>

      <t>
        If mandatory locking is enforced, then the data server must also
        ensure that to return only information that is within
        the owner’s locked byte range.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="READ_PLUS with Sparse Files Example">
    <t>
      The following table describes a sparse file.  For each byte
      range, the file contains either non-zero data or a hole. In addition,
      the server in this example will only create a hole if it is greater
      than 32K.
    </t>

    <texttable anchor="space_example">
      <ttcol align='left' >Byte-Range</ttcol>
      <ttcol align='left' >Contents</ttcol>

      <c>0-15999    </c> <c>Hole    </c>
      <c>16K-31999  </c> <c>Non-Zero</c>
      <c>32K-255999 </c> <c>Hole    </c>
      <c>256K-287999</c> <c>Non-Zero</c>
      <c>288K-353999</c> <c>Hole    </c>
      <c>354K-417999</c> <c>Non-Zero</c>
    </texttable>

    <t>
      Under the given circumstances, if a client was to read from
      the file with a max read size of 64K, the following will be
      the results for the given READ_PLUS calls.  This assumes the
      client has already opened the file, acquired a valid stateid
      ('s' in the example), and just needs to issue READ_PLUS
      requests.
    </t>

    <t>
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>
          READ_PLUS(s, 0, 64K) --> NFS_OK, eof = false, &lt;data[0,32K], hole[32K,224K]&gt;.
          Since the first hole is less than the server's minimum hole size, the
          first 32K of the file is returned as data and the remaining 32K is
          returned as a hole which actually extends to 256K.
        </t>

        <t>
          READ_PLUS(s, 32K, 64K) --> NFS_OK, eof = false, &lt;hole[32K,224K]&gt;
          The requested range was all zeros, and the current hole begins at offset 32K and is 224K
          in length. Note that the client should not have followed up the previous
          READ_PLUS request with this one as the hole information from the previous
          call extended past what the client was requesting.
        </t>

        <t>
          READ_PLUS(s, 256K, 64K) --> NFS_OK, eof = false, &lt;data[256K, 288K], hole[288K, 354K]&gt;.
          Returns an array of the 32K data and the hole which extends to 354K.
        </t>

        <t>
          READ_PLUS(s, 354K, 64K) --> NFS_OK, eof = true, &lt;data[354K, 418K]&gt;.
          Returns the final 64K of data and informs the client there is no more data in the file.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
