<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2014) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2014) -->

<section anchor="ss:pnfs" title="pNFS considerations for New Operations">
  <section anchor="ss:pnfs:atom" title="Atomicity for ALLOCATE and DEALLOCATE">
    <t>
      Both ALLOCATE (see <xref target='op:allocate' />) and
      DEALLOCATE (see <xref target='op:deallocate' />) are sent to the
      metadata server, which is responsible for coordinating the
      changes onto the storage devices. In particular, both operations
      must either fully succeed or fail, it cannot be the case that
      one storage device succeeds whilst another fails.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="ss:pnfs:stateids" title="Sharing of stateids with NFSv4.1">
    <t>
      A NFSv4.2 metadata server can hand out a layout to a NFSv4.1
      storage device. Section 13.9.1 of <xref target='RFC5661' />
      discusses how the client gets a stateid from the metadata
      server to present to a storage device.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="ss:pnfs:flt" title="NFSv4.2 as a Storage Protocol in pNFS: the File Layout Type">
    <t>
      A file layout provided by a NFSv4.2 server may refer either to a storage device
      that only implements NFSv4.1 as specified in <xref target='RFC5661' />,
      or to a storage device that implements additions from NFSv4.2, in which
      case the rules in <xref target='ss:pnfs:ops' /> apply. As the File
      Layout Type does not provide a means for informing the client as
      to which minor version a particular storage device is providing, the client will have
      to negotiate this with the storage device via the normal RPC semantics of major and minor
      version discovery. E.g., as per Section 16.2.3 of <xref target='RFC5661' />, the
      client could try a COMPOUND with a minorversion of 2 and if it gets
      NFS4ERR_MINOR_VERS_MISMATCH, drop back to 1.
    </t>

    <section anchor="ss:pnfs:ops" title="Operations Sent to NFSv4.2 Data Servers">
      <t>
        In addition to the commands listed in <xref target='RFC5661' />,
        NFSv4.2 data servers MAY accept a COMPOUND containing the following
        additional operations: IO_ADVISE (see <xref target='op:io_advise' />),
        READ_PLUS (see <xref target='op:read_plus' />), WRITE_SAME (see
        <xref target='op:write_same' />), and SEEK (see
        <xref target='op:seek' />), which will be treated like the
        subset specified as "Operations Sent to NFSv4.1 Data Servers"
        in Section 13.6 of <xref target='RFC5661' />.
      </t>

      <t>
        Additional details on the implementation of these operations in a pNFS
        context are documented in the operation specific sections.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
