<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2011-2012) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2011-2012) -->

<section anchor="op:copy_notify" title="Operation 61: COPY_NOTIFY - Notify a source server of a future copy">
  <section toc='exclude' title="ARGUMENT">
    <?rfc include='autogen/copy_notify_args.xml'?>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="RESULT">
    <?rfc include='autogen/copy_notify_res.xml'?>
  </section>

  <section toc='exclude' title="DESCRIPTION">
    <t>
      This operation is used for an inter-server copy. A client
      sends this operation in a COMPOUND request to the source
      server to authorize a destination server identified by
      cna_destination_server to read the file specified by
      CURRENT_FH on behalf of the given user.
    </t>

    <t>
      The cna_destination_server MUST be specified using the
      netloc4 network location format. The server is not required
      to resolve the cna_destination_server address before completing
      this operation.
    </t>

    <t>
      If this operation succeeds, the source server will allow the
      cna_destination_server to copy the specified file on behalf
      of the given user. If COPY_NOTIFY succeeds, the destination
      server is granted permission to read the file as long as both
      of the following conditions are met:
    </t>

    <t>
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>
          The destination server begins reading the source file
          before the cnr_lease_time expires. If the cnr_lease_time
          expires while the destination server is still reading
          the source file, the destination server is allowed to
          finish reading the file.
        </t>

        <t>
          The client has not issued a COPY_REVOKE for
          the same combination of user, filehandle,
          and destination server.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>

    <t>
      The cnr_lease_time is chosen by the source server. A
      cnr_lease_time of 0 (zero) indicates an infinite lease. To
      renew the copy lease time the client should resend the same
      copy notification request to the source server.
    </t>

    <t>
      To avoid the need for synchronized clocks, copy lease times
      are granted by the server as a time delta. However, there is a
      requirement that the client and server clocks do not drift
      excessively over the duration of the lease. There is also the
      issue of propagation delay across the network which could easily
      be several hundred milliseconds as well as the possibility that
      requests will be lost and need to be retransmitted.
    </t>

    <t>
      To take propagation delay into account, the client should
      subtract it from copy lease times (e.g., if the client estimates
      the one-way propagation delay as 200 milliseconds, then it can
      assume that the lease is already 200 milliseconds old when it gets
      it). In addition, it will take another 200 milliseconds to get a
      response back to the server. So the client must send a lease
      renewal or send the copy offload request to the cna_destination_server
      at least 400 milliseconds before the copy lease would expire. If
      the propagation delay varies over the life of the lease (e.g., the
      client is on a mobile host), the client will need to continuously
      subtract the increase in propagation delay from the copy lease times.
    </t>

    <t>
      The server's copy lease period configuration should take into
      account the network distance of the clients that will be
      accessing the server's resources. It is expected that the lease
      period will take into account the network propagation delays and
      other network delay factors for the client population. Since the
      protocol does not allow for an automatic method to determine an
      appropriate copy lease period, the server's administrator may have
      to tune the copy lease period.
    </t>

    <t>
      A successful response will also contain a list of names, addresses,
      and URLs called cnr_source_server, on which the source is willing to
      accept connections from the destination. These might not be reachable
      from the client and might be located on networks to which the client
      has no connection.
    </t>

    <t>
      If the client wishes to perform an inter-server copy, the client
      MUST send a COPY_NOTIFY to the source server. Therefore, the source
      server MUST support COPY_NOTIFY.
    </t>

    <t>
      For a copy only involving one server (the source and destination
      are on the same server), this operation is unnecessary.
    </t>

    <t>
      The COPY_NOTIFY operation may fail for the following reasons
      (this is a partial list):
    </t>

    <t>
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>NFS4ERR_MOVED</t>
        <t>NFS4ERR_NOTSUPP</t>
        <t>NFS4ERR_WRONGSEC</t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
